Guide to the Collection of Bookplates by John W. Evans
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Bookplates by John W. Evans
1917-1942
BKP 127
Yale University Arts Library
0.42
(1 box)
This collection includes bookplates designed by John W. Evans (1855-1943), a master wood engraver born in Brooklyn, NY.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011, it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John William Evans (1855-1943) was an American engraver and graphic artist born in Brooklyn, NY. A master wood engraver, Evans created reproductions of famous paintings and other works to illustrate magazines such as Century, Harper's, and Scribner's. In "retirement," Evans took up bookplate design. His award-winning wood engraving was exhibited in the Paris Exposition of 1900, the Chicago Exposition of 1903, and the Panama Exposition of 1915. Evans had close associations with other bookplate artists, including Timothy Cole and William Fowler Hopson, who was Evans's brother-in-law. He was also a longtime and active member of the Freemasons.
Reference: "John W. Evans, at 84, Still Active Master of Wood Engraving Craft," Brooklyn Daily Eagle, February 20, 1938.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes a number of bookplates designed by John W. Evans (1855-1943), a master wood engraver born in Brooklyn, NY. The bookplates were designed primarily for private individuals, including several for his friends and family. The collection also includes four woodblocks for Evans's bookplate designs and a letter written by Evans to his sister, Ada Hopson.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Bookplates. II. Correspondence and Ephemera. III. Woodblocks.
Bookplates, American; Wood-engraving; Bookplates; Wood blocks (printing blocks); Evans, John William, 1855-1943
- Bookplates, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged numerically, according to accompanying checklist.
  - #1. Alice Ritchie, 1939; 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - #2. Nöel and Alma Lewis, 1939; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - #3. Joan Hutzelman, 1938; 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - #4. Robert A. Hutzelman, Jr., 1938-1939; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - #5. Edna Huntington, 1937; 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - #6. Agatha Palumbo, 1938; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - #7. Arthur A. Bourgeois, 1939; 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - #8. John W. Evans, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - #9. Randolph Macon Women's College (Louise Jordan Smith), undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - #10. Johanna Erika Ruthven von Tiling, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - #11. (Christmas Greetings and Good Health), 1927; 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - #13. W. F. Hopson, 193 undated; 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - #15. Cornelia Eames and Frank Dell Anthony, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - #16. Timothy Cole, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - #17. James Harrison Wilson, 1917; 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - #18. Alice and Edmond Kiechlin, 1939; 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - #19. J. Foster Mech, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - #20. George Hope Ryder, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - #21. Elizabeth and Edmund Pope, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - #22. Evalyn Evans Lindars, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - #23. Edna May Lindars, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - #24. George Albert Simons, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - #25. Clara S. T. Wayland, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - #26. Ann Burg, 1939; 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - #27. Therese, Rosemary, and John W. Evans, Jr., 1939; 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - #28. Evan Evans, [1938?]; 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - #29. Gordon Evans, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - #30. Audubon Club of Erasmus High School, 1919 undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - #31. (Lakeside Etching), undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - #32. (Holiday Greetings), undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - #33. Evelyn and Jack Henry, 1938; 1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - #34. Charles and Edith Gaynor, 1939; 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - #35. Felix Gordon Evans, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - #36. Edna May and Robert A. Hutzelman, 1938; 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - #37. John W. Evans, Jr., 1917 undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - #38. Theo. A. Taylor, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - #39. John W. Evans, 1919; 2 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - #40. Ind. W. Lindars, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - #41. (Grampy's Tree), 1942 undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Scope and Contents
    This folder includes an illustration for a Christmas / New Year's greeting card.
  - #42. Wm. and Ada Hopson, 1941; 2 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Correspondence and Ephemera, Series II
  - Correspondence and Ephemera, 1938 undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    The folder contains the following: a piece of correspondence between John W. Evans and Ada Hopson (undated); a newspaper article about John W. Evans published in the Brooklyn Daily Eagle, February 20, 1938; and a handwritten checklist of the materials in the collection.
- Wood blocks, Series III
  - Evans bookplate for Mrs. W.F.H.; wood engraving., undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Evans wood block bookplate for W.F.H., undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 43)